Can you students hear me?
>> Hello. Can anybody hear me?
>> Yes. Yes.
>> Good.
All right, folks. I'll wait for a few
more seconds till we have maybe
100 students and then I'll begin.
Actually before I share let me stop
sharing
and uh
share with some
okay let's begin. So
today we are sort of shifting gears and
we are going to discuss what neural
networks actually represent.
So far what we've seen is that neural
networks are universal approximators.
They can model any boolean categorical
or real valued function. They can check
static inputs for patterns. They can
scan for patterns and they can analyze
time series for patterns. But in each
case they must be trained to make their
predictions. In the process of being
trained, what do they learn internally?
What does the network actually
represent? That's going to be the
primary topic of today's lecture. And
we'll build on this in the next couple
of lectures to see how these this the uh
intuitions we discuss and develop today
can be used for generative models.
So here's the problem of learning in a
network.
You're given a collection of input
output pairs like those shown by these
red lines. And from just this collection
of input output pairs, you must learn
the function that the network actually
represents.
So in a classification network what the
classification uh setup what that would
mean is that you that you'll be given
data of this kind data from the two
classes where each data instance is
labeled with its class. In my picture
here the classes are shown by color. So
you might be told that all of these dots
belong to the red class. All of these
dots belong to the blue class. And from
just these training instances, you have
to learn the decision boundaries which
in this example are the double
pentagonal regions. So in effect from
just these training data points, you
must learn the function shown to the
right which has a value outside the
double of zero outside the double
pentagon and one inside the double
pentagon. That's how you would learn to
classify between the two classes.
But in reality, the data you're given
are not going to be like this where the
red data and the blue data are cleanly
separated.
Often you're going to have some blue
instances within the red data, you're
going to have some red dots within the
blue region and somehow from this
jumbled up data, you must still learn
this function.
In this case, what is the function we
learn?
Now to get a better idea, let's look at
a much more trivial example than this
one.
>> Yeah.
>> Is it the same from
>> Can you please mute yourselves guys?
Okay.
So instead of looking at something as
complex as this, let's look at a much
simpler problem of just a linear
classifier which we know can be modeled
by a single perceptron. So here's a two
dimensional example. Here you'll be
given training data of this kind red and
blue dots again and from this we must
learn a linear classifier such that all
the red which learns a linear boundary
such that all the red dots are on one
side and the blue are on the other side.
So basically we want to learn a heavy
side function of this kind which where
there's a linear hyper plane separating
the two sides. On one side the function
value is zero and the other side the
function value is one. Except we have a
problem. The data themselves are not
cleanly separable. So you have some red
dots hanging over the blue dots on the
blue side and you have some blue dots
lying on the floor on the red side of
the plane. So given data of this kind,
how could we learn such a function?
Let me simplify it further to a
one-dimensional example because it's
easy to visualize. In the
one-dimensional case, here's the kind of
data you'd have. The input feature is
one-dimensional. The data labels are
either zero, which are these blue dots,
are one, which are these red dots. And
we still want to learn a linear
classifier. What is a linear classifier
for one-dimensional data? Anyone? What
would a linear classifier be for
onedimensional data? Can somebody tell
me?
Anybody?
Anyone guys? a single a line
in one dimensions a line is going to be
the entire x-axis. Right?
So remember in two dimensions
a linear classifier is a is is a line.
In three dimensions a linear classifier
is going to be a hyper plane. In one
dimension a linear classifier is going
to be a threshold. So, uh, threshold
over here. Is there a threshold that
clearly cleanly separates the red and
the blue data over here? Is there a
linear classifier in this example that
separates the two classes? Do you see
one? Nope. Right? It doesn't exist. So,
how can we learn a linear classifier
from such data? Now we know that a
neural network is is is arbitrarily
has arbitrary capacity depending on the
size of the network. So it's fully
possible that your neural network ends
up learning a function of this kind
which gets zero error on the training
data.
But is this a function you really want?
Is this what we'd want the network to
learn?
No. Right? But let's just assume that
this is fine. We are happy to learn such
a function.
What would we do even in that case? If I
had a situation of this kind where I
have a bunch of training data points
where the x value is the same for all
the points but some of them are colored
blue and some of them are colored red.
So say maybe I have a 100 training data
points all with the same x value. 90 of
them have class value one so they're
colored red. And 10 of them are class
value zero so they're colored blue. In
this case for this particular value of X
what must be what must the output of the
network be? Should it be one indicating
red or zero indicating blue or maybe 0.9
indicating that 90% of the data that
it's seen at this X value belong to
class one. Which of these three make the
most sense? Makes the most sense.
Anyone?
So
any answers what would you want the
output of the network would be right?
So one for the one that makes most sense
is going to be 0.9 right because
this carries the information
that
there are there's more than one class
possible at this value of x. Moreover,
it also carries the information that 90%
of the data at this value of x belong to
class one. You can always convert that
to say, you know, because this fraction
is more than 0.5, I'll call everything
that has this value of x one. That's a
that's a subsequent decision you can
make. But the most informative thing you
can do is to actually indicate the
fraction of all instances that have the
class value one at this x. Would you
agree with that? Yes or no? Give me
thumbs ups if you say if you agree with
it, right? Or at least have a yes.
That's like only two people.
Maybe I can get 25 people agreeing with
me because this is important, right?
Okay. 17. I'll go with that. Okay, guys.
So, this is important, right? It makes
more sense for us to indicate the
fraction of all instances that have the
class value one. But what happens if I
just nudge all these data points so that
they're not all at the same x? They all
differ from one another by 10 raised to
minus17 which is the uh resolution of a
32-bit floatingoint number. In this
case, should the function be going up
and down arbitrarily or does it still
make sense for you to say that the
fraction of all instances at at this
around this value of x that belong to
class one is 0.9?
Which makes more sense? If all the none
of them have the same x, but they're
infinitismly close, would you want the
function to be going up and down or
would you just want it to indicate 0.9
which makes more sense, right?
The V minus is 0.9, right? 0.9. So that
makes more sense, right? What's magical
about 10 to -7.
How far apart must the data be before
you agree that maybe the answer is not
really 0.9? Do we have an answer to
that?
What do you guys think?
Yes. No.
I haven't yet given you an answer.
Right?
So let's look at the problem slightly
differently. At each x, instead of
looking at just that value of x, let me
look at a small window of x values
around it to account for the fact that
you can have perturbations.
And then instead of just plotting the y
value at that x, I'm going to plot the
average y value of all training data
instances within this window over here.
that average y-v value is going to be
zero because all training data instances
have a class of zero out here. But then
as I begin sliding this forward, at some
point I'm going to begin seeing
instances from the from class one. And
now this average begins to go up. And as
I keep going forward, that average will
keep increasing until eventually I get
to a point where I see no more blue data
points. And then the average itself is
just going to be one.
This makes more sense, does it not? It
actually allows for you to give you the
fraction and allows for perturbations.
Would you agree?
Right. You're still still left with a
question of how wide must this window be
for this to make sense?
And I'm saying we don't even need to
make that decision. This is where we
fall back on math. First this function
here, we all recognize it. What is this
function guys?
What is this one here? The sigmoid,
right? So what is the sigmoid actually
giving us? The sigmoid is giving when I
think speak of the fraction of all
training data points at a particular
value of x that have class value one.
That is basically the probability of
class value one given that x. Right?
Would you agree that this fraction over
here is actually P of Y = 1 given X?
Right? Yes or no? Right? And so the
sigmoid is actually giving us P of Y = 1
given X. And here's the function that is
the uh uh sigmoid function. We're all
very familiar with with it. It's 1 / 1 +
e - w + w1x. Now, what's the difference
between the soft max function and the
sigmoid? Anyone? What's the difference
between the soft max and the sigmoid? Do
you know
range?
The soft max is basically just a
sigmoid. The soft max is the multiclass
version of the sigmoid. But if you
looked at any one class, that function
is going to look like a sigmoid. So the
soft max is just a generalization of the
sigmoid. anything I say of sigmoids also
hold also for soft maxes. So
let's start with this with this
intuition that the sigmoid function
gives you the posterior probability of
class one of the target class given the
x value. So a sigmoid perceptron with a
single input which is going to have w1x
plus w0. This models the a posterior
posteriority probability of class one
given that single x a sigmoid with a
multi-dimensional input is still going
to give you exactly the same situation.
In the two dimensional example that we
saw earlier we had blue dots on the red
side, red dots on the blue side. There's
no clear line that will separate the two
colors. But still this is exactly just a
generalization of the one-dimensional
problem we saw earlier. Here too you
would use a sigmoid and at any given in
location X the value of the sigmoid is
going to give you the posterior
probability of class one given that X
and this of course is just the function
of the sigmoid function for the sigmoid.
So a a sigmoid perceptron with
multi-dimensional input also computes
the posterior probability of class one
of the target class given the input X.
That making sense to you guys?
Yes. No.
David. Okay. All right. But we know that
a sigmoid is a linear classifier. How is
this a linear classifier? This function
doesn't look linear. It's actually a
curve. It's a sheet that has folded.
Right? So, how is that a linear
classifier? Can anyone tell me how is
this a linear classifier?
Anybody?
Any guesses?
Okay, I'll give you 10 seconds. If you
guys can't reply, I'll give you the
answer. Any guesses? Why is this a
linear classifier?
So
because if I if I have to decide at any
point what is the class is it class zero
or class one the way I would do it is to
say I'm going is to assign a threshold
to this and say if this guy is greater
than say 0.5 I'm going to call it class
one otherwise I'll call it class zero.
If you look at the locust of all points
where this value is is point exactly 0.5
that's going to be a line in this case
more generally it's going to be a hyper
plane. So the boundary between the
regions of the input where this function
is greater than 0.5 and less than 0.5
that boundary is going to be a hyper
plane or any threshold it doesn't have
to be 0.5. So because these boundaries
are linear although the function itself
is not linear the classifier is linear.
That make sense to everybody.
Fine. So sigmoids and soft max functions
are multi- are linear classifiers.
Now how do we estimate this? This also
goes back and relates to how we decide
the width of that uh window within which
we compute fractions. I said we don't.
Now the sigmoid function says that the
probability of class Y equals = 1 given
X is simply 1 / 1 + E RA - W + W1X. I'm
using a one-dimensional example but this
is true for any number of dimensions.
Right? You would be given training data
which have many XY pairs represented by
these dots. And from this we have to
estimate the W's. How will we do it?
First this P of Y given X is actually
the probability of Y = 1 given X. That's
this orange curve. What is the
probability of Y = -1 given X? The
probability of Y = -1 given X is simply
going to be 1 minus P of Y = 1 given X.
Right? So P of Y = -1
given X is going to be 1 - P of this is
a P guys
P of Y = 1 given X easy enough which
again if you so if I take a 1 minus this
term over here that's going to become
1 + E to minus whatever
I'll call this Z -1 /
1 + E - Z.
These ones cancel out. So I get E - Z
over 1 + E - Z. If I divide the
numerator and denominator by e minus Z,
that becomes 1 + e to
1 / e - z is just e to z + 1. Right? So
basically the probability of y = -1
given x is the same as the probability
of y = 1 given x except the sign of this
term becomes positive. That make sense
to everybody?
Yes or no?
Can I see a few more yeses? Now I can
write this all jointly, right? and say p
of y = any given y = x is 1 / 1 + e
minus of y * w 0 + w1x. You can see that
when y = 1 this becomes this y that just
ends up as this formula. When my y= -1
minus and minus become plus that ends up
as this formula. So this this is a
common way of representing both these
formula.
Is that clear everybody? Do you see
this?
Right. Okay. So,
we have agreed on this. Now, let's go
back. We want to estimate the model. We
are given a bunch of training data which
are XY pairs.
X's are vectors. Y's are binary, you
know, one minus one class values. What
is the total probability of all of my
training data? Assume assuming they're
all independent and identically
distributed. The joint probability of
all my training data is the product over
all instances of the probability of the
individual training instances which is P
of Xbar. Right? But the p of x i yi can
I can decompose this using base rule as
p of x i times p of yi given x i and I
furthermore I can decompose this as a
product of this term
and of course p of x i is over here this
guy according to our model is given by
the sigma. So is this formula making
sense? This is the joint probability of
all of our training data instances. Is
this making sense to you guys? Right.
Yes. No. Okay. Give me 10 thumbs ups and
I'll move on. Right. Because
All right. So
the joint probability of all my training
data is the product over all training
instances of P of X I times the sigmoid
computed at that XI with that YI which
again I can separate as product of all
all the XI's times the product of all
the sigmoids.
If I take the log of the probability of
the training data, that's simply going
to be because multiplication becomes a
summation and log this guy simply
becomes the sum over all training
instances of log of P of XI and this one
instances of log of the sigmoid.
Now
>> guys, can you mute yourselves, please?
I'm sure that was not intended for the
class to record and put up on YouTube.
Okay,
anybody who wants to speak into this,
remember that anything you might be
saying to anybody in the middle of class
is going to be put up on YouTube and
heard by thousands of people. If you're
interested in your privacy, please keep
your mic microphones turned off, right?
Okay. Anyway, so did this make sense?
The log of the training data of the
probability of the training data, yes or
no?
Okay.
So
now there's something called the maximum
likelihood training principle. How many
of you are familiar with it?
Have you heard the term maximum
likelihood training?
So what is the maximum likelihood
training principle? Anybody?
What is the maximum likelihood training
principle? Do you know?
>> Yes, Prof. I'm familiar with it.
>> So what is it? Yeah. So basically it
helps uh to measure how complex the the
classifier is. If I have like a point
here and another uh underneath I can I
can like draw a line and separate to see
how
>> that's talking about a specific model.
No that's not what the maximum
likelihood training principle is. The
maximum likelihood training principle
says that whatever data you are training
your training data you've got is very
typical of the underlying process. So
given a collection of possible models to
choose from the model that you will
choose is the model that assigns the
maximum possible probab maximum
probability to your training data
because the assumption is that your
training data are typical. They're
highly probable. So the maximum for any
statistical model the maximum likelihood
estimation procedure says find me the
parameters of the model that maximize
the log probability of the training
data. This is based on the principle
that your training data are so typical
that it's extremely probable that your
process would have generated them. That
make sense?
Yes. No.
Right. Okay. And here of course this guy
is not a function of the model
parameters. So this simply reduces to
maximizing
the log of the sigmoids or alternatively
minimizing the negative log of the
sigmoids.
This as it turns out is simply
the cross entropy between the one hot
labels for the training data and the
probability assigned to them by the
sigmoid. So this guy here is identical
to minimizing the kale divergence
between the desired output and the
actual output. So maximum likel
likelihood training of a logistic
minimizes the kale divergence between
its output and the target output. It
cannot be solved directly. It means
gradient descent. Nevertheless, the key
point is that when you train a logistic
function or a soft max function, you are
actually performing maximum likelihood
training to estimate a model that gives
you the best possible estimate in a
maximum likelihood sense of the
posterior probabilities for the target
classes. Did that make sense?
So basically you're estimating the model
parameters such that the probability for
the target class is maximized.
Now this was for a linear classifier,
right? Single logistic function. What
about data like this? These are
nonlinear classifiers.
What happens here?
Now first consider the simple case where
the classes are in fact cleanly
separable. So you don't have any blue
dots on the red side or vice versa,
right? The net must learn to classify.
So if I have a sufficient net for this
data, then we know that I can do this
using one subnet for the first pentagon,
a second subnet for the second pentagon
and then a final R. So let me say that
I've given you this actual network. I've
not just not given you the parameters.
And now we must estimate the parameters,
the weights for all the connections of
this network using these data. Now what
do we know about this final guy? This is
a
perceptron. Say it's a logistic. What
kind of classifier is this final
perceptron? Anybody? We've just been
discussing it. What kind of classifier
is this final perceptron? Anyone?
It's a linear classifier, right? If it's
a linear classifier, then what does it
say about the data that it sees to be
able to classify which are the outputs
of these two subn networks for it to be
able to classify the two data two
classes perfectly? What does it say
about the these the outputs from these
guys?
Anybody?
They must be
out here. This final perceptron is a
linear classifier.
But this final perceptron is a linear
classifier over these features. Yes or
no?
Right? And so what this means is that if
you look at these features y1 and y2 and
you plot those features for the training
data
the in the y1 y2 space the two although
the classes began in this jumbled manner
by the time the network is done with it
in the y1 y2 space the classes must be
linearly separable otherwise this final
classifier cannot separate the two
classes.
Do you see that? Yes or no?
Right. Can I see some thumbs up for
that? Thumbs ups for that. Like 10. Not
being greedy.
All right. Okay. So, what's happening
over here? What is actually happening is
that this rest of the network which
moves the data into the Y1 Y2 space,
it's actually a transformation that
transforms the data from this input
space where they're all jumbled into
another space where they are linearly
separable. So the network in fact
consists of two components. one as this
final linear classifier and the rest is
the rest of this network all the way
until the penultimate layer
which converts these data into being
linearly separable.
It's a feature transformer that moves
the data around till they're linearly
separable.
That making sense
to everybody?
Okay. Can I give get 10 thumbs ups? So I
know this made sense.
Okay.
Right. Now this is true of any
sufficient structure not just the
optimal one. If even if I connected
everything up like this it doesn't
matter. We know the network can always
so long as the network has more capacity
than required. We know that the network
can act always classify the data
perfectly. And so when it learns to
classify the data perfectly, what is
happening is that the rest of the
network is moving these data around
until they are linearly separable. And
the final classifier is learning the
linear separator. If this network is not
doesn't have sufficient capacity, even
in this case, the network is still going
to try to attempt to move these data
around until they are as linearly
separable as possible. And then this guy
is going to try to learn a linear linear
classifier. In this case, it won't
perfectly separate the two classes, but
it's still going to try to do the best
job it can. That make sense
to everyone?
Yes. No. Okay. I see one or two yeses. I
will move on. Right. So, that leads us
to our first point.
Okay, 10 seconds, guys.
and did that early.
Anybody want to take a guess? What are
the two answers? Both are true, right?
The portion of the network until the
second to last layer is essentially a
feature extraction module that extracts
linearly separable features for the
classes. The output layer is a linear
classifier that can only perform well if
the rest of the network performs the
input space transforms the input space
such that the classes are linearly
separable. Right? We got that.
But then here's a more typical setting.
What we just saw was where the two
classes were separable even though the
boundary was not linear like in the
double pentagon case. But in a real life
setting, you're not actually going to
see this clean data where you have only
red dots in the red region and blue dots
in the blue region. They're going to
have some leakage. Some blue in the red,
some red in the blue. So the boundaries
are going to be kind of fuzzy, right? In
this setting, what happens
here too? The feature extraction portion
of the network is going to try to move
the data around until they are almost
linearly separable, like shown in this
picture.
And then now the posterior probability
is going to be modeled
uh the by the is modeled by this
logistic and it's still a maximum
likelihood estimator. So it's going and
we know that the posterior probability
the the likelihood assigned by the
logistic is maximized when the when the
classes are linearly separable. And so
this is going to move the data around
until they are as linearly separable as
possible.
So that this can model it with a uh
logistic function. That making sense to
everybody?
Yes. No. Give me some thumbs ups. Okay.
And so
again
mathematically what's happening the
output logistic function this guy is
working in the y space right. Let me
call this y= f ofx. So or this y1 y2
space let me call this y1 y2 space f ofx
and the output of the network equals
itself is y. So it's going to be this
logistic is working on
the function computed by this portion of
the network. And so the logistic
function is computing the posterior
probability of the classes given the
output of this network. But if there's a
onetoone relationship between the input
and the output of the network, that's
exactly the same as P of Y given X. And
so the output logistic in fact computes
the posterior probability of the classes
uh you know from the feature extraction
layer which is just the same as the
posterior probability of the class given
the input X.
Is this making sense here that even for
the nonlinear classifier this is what
the network is computing provided you
have a logistic function here or a
softmax that making sense to everybody?
Yes. No. Can you give me some thumbs
ups?
Okay, guys. Be a little prompt because
otherwise it'll slow us down. Okay. All
right. And so
when the data are not not separable, the
boundaries are not linear, the output of
the network is still P of Y given X. For
multiclass networks, it will be a vector
of a posterior class probabilities. If
you're training the network to minimize
the KL divergence, the parameters of
both the final softmax and the network
are learned to maximize the posterior
probability of the classes given the
input X. So when you train the network,
what you're really performing although
you may not be thinking about it
explicitly is maximum likelihood
training of the network. So in fact
you're performing statistical estimation
of the parameters of the network. This
is a statistical model. The neural
network is a statistical model. It's
learning probabilities. That making
sense to everybody?
Yes. No.
Okay.
So,
nine. Some I find it it's hard for the
class to come up with a 10th. Thumbs up.
Does that matter? Okay.
Here's the second P
15 seconds, guys.
All right, let me stop this here.
Anybody want to give me the answer?
alum
1 2 and four. Right? A classification
neural network is just a statistical
model that computes the a postiorary
probability of the classes given the
inputs. Training training the network to
minimize the cross entropy loss is the
same as maximum likelihood training of
the network. It's valid and possibly
beneficial to train the network and
subsequently replace the final layer by
any other linear classifier because once
you train the network the classes have
become linearly separable. Once you have
linearly separable classes you can toss
in any other kind of linear classifier.
Uh it's no the three it it's going to
give you a maximum likelihood estimate
of the network parameters regardless of
whether the classes are actually
separable or not. It's going to try to
separate the classes as much as possible
even if it doesn't succeed. That's
exactly what we discussed over here.
Right? In this case, you're going to end
up with something like this.
All right. So, moving on the story so
far, a classification NLP actually
comprises two components. a feature
extraction network that converts the
inputs into linearly separable features
or nearly linearly separable features
and a final linear classifier that
operates on the linearly separable
features using a softmax. The final
layer of the network actually computes
the eight posterior probabilities of
classes. Training the network to minim
minimize scale divergence is identical
to maximum like pair training of the
network. Is everybody good with this or
do we have any questions before we move
on?
Okay. Can I have those 10 thumbs ups?
That's all I'm asking. It seems to die
at night. Okay. So, we've seen what
happens all the way up to Y1 and Y2.
Right now, skip this. What happens in
the rest of the network? How do the
lower layers respond? They too compute
features. But what do they look look
like? Now what we know is that as the
data goes through the network from X the
X X space to this Y space the data
eventually become linearly separable
right so there's a manifold hypothesis
which says that as you go through the
network the network manipulates and
twists and untwists the surf the space
that this data lie in until they
eventually end up in a space where they
are linearly separable. So the layers
sequentially straighten the data
manifold
on and so that the classes become
linearly separable and then the final
layer of course uh performs
classification onwards. So what does
that mean? Let's take a example of a
very simp a simple toy example where
we're trying to separate two classes the
blue and the red class here and the
boundary between the two is a perfect
circle.
We're going to try to learn a linear
classifier for this data. A neural
network classifier and MLP for this
data. And the MLP has one hidden layer.
And that one hidden layer has three
neurons. And the three neurons are uh
all have tanage activation. So what
happens when you try when you perform
inference in this network? First you
start off with the X then
this the W1 over here which are these
weights. So at the input to this guy
you're going to get Z equ=
W1
X right then you have the tanage
activation you're going to get Y0
or Y = tanh of Z.
Then
there's this W2 over here, right? And
then out here you're going to get Z equ=
W2 * Y0
y 0. And then this of course is your
linear classifier. Is the sequence of
operations making sense to everybody?
Yes. No. Okay. The input is
two-dimensional.
What is the dimensionality of Z?
How many dimensions do
does Z live in?
Anyone? Three. Right? Because I've gone
from two to three. So Z lives in three
dimensions.
The Z is in a three-dimensional space.
But now if the input is a is in two
dimensions, the entire input lies on a
two-dimensional plane. Z has three
components.
So Z lives in a three-dimensional space.
But will this X after being transformed
as Z= WX occupy the entire
three-dimensional space or only some
small region of it? What do you guys
think? Is it going to is it going to
occupy the entire space or just some
small region of it? What region will it
occupy?
So what region will it occupy? It's
going to occupy a plane, right? It
starts off as a plane. WZ wx is going to
be a is a linear transform. So in this
three-dimensional space, it's still the
data are going to live in a
twodimensional
hyper plane, two-dimensional plane in
this three-dimensional space. That's
what Z is going to look like. But it's
going to be a plane, right? But then you
transform each of the three dimensions
using tanh and each of them get
transformed differently because tanh is
not linear. So what happens when you get
to here? Does it remain a plane
after the activation? Will it remain a
plane? What do you guys think?
If each point is transformed,
will it remain a plane?
Yes. No.
No. because each component is going to
be transformed in a slightly different
way. Tanh is not a linear operator. So
now what happens is that in the y space
it's no longer going to be a plane. It's
going to be some curved two-dimensional
surface. It's still going to be a
two-dimensional surface, but it's going
to be a nonlinear surface. That making
sense?
Yes. No.
Right. But then I perform w2 * y, right?
to get zed. What is the dimensionality
of this Z over here? What is the
dimensionality of this guy?
It's one. It's just a line, right? So
this and where will it be? This W
represents some
axis in in some three in this
threedimensional space. And this Z value
is going to be projections on this W
vector. That make sense?
is the inner product between the Y's and
this Z.
Did that make sense to everybody?
Okay, so let's see what actually
happens. This animation was produced by
Ander Zolan, one of my students. And you
can see what happens as the network
learns. It learns to move this
two-dimensional surface around in 3D
space so that it gets positioned. Then
the tanage distorts this plane into this
curved surface. Then the second
operation projects that entire curved
surface onto the weight vector. And so
this is what that looks like.
And then initially you'll find that the
reds and the blues are all over the
place. But then once it finds the right
positioning for this guy and it finds
the right W for the second guy, the
projection of this of this folded
surface onto W onto this new vector is
such that all the blues lie on one side
and all the reds lie on the other side
at which point a threshold separates the
reds and the blues and so you get a
decision boundary of this kind. Does
that make sense?
So basically what happens you start off
with this guy then you find out how to
position it in 3D space then the tan h
is going to sort of warp this 3D space
somehow right and make this curved
curved sheet then you find the W vector
such that when you project every data
point onto this W vector all the reds
all the blue guys fall on one side of
one point and all the red guys fall on
the other side. Now you can just put a
threshold over here and that actually
ends up learning a perfectly circular uh
or in this case it's not yet circular
but it learns something that kind of
approximates the original decision
bound. Did did the process by which the
whole thing happened. I mean was it
clear to you guys what happened over
here? So
what we are learning is how to position
this guy
in this 3D space such that when the
activation walks the surface then there
is a vector W such that when the surface
is projected onto the W the blues and
the reds separate out we also learn this
other W. So as you go through the
network the it keeps warping these
surfaces to make the the classes more
and more linearly separable. That was
for two dimen two classes. Here is
another example where we are doing this
on safar. There are 10 classes
uh a safhar 10 and uh uh this was a uh
11 layer network
and we're projecting the representations
of the data in each of the layers into
two dimensions for visibility. And you
can see what happens. Initially all the
data are very mixed up. Each color
represents a different class, different
uh image class. As you go through the
layers, the classes become increasingly
linearly separable till when they get to
about these 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 the ninth
layer, they're already linearly
separable. After which subsequent layers
simply increase the spacing between
classes. Actually, let's see this in
three dimensions.
And you can see what is happening over
here. Right? As you go through the data,
the layers, the classes becoming
increasingly separable until by here
they're already linearly separable. And
then afterwards you're only increasing
the separation between classes which is
why the final layer can easily learn to
uh classify the data. This making sense
the visualization
right and so here's the interesting
thing. The classes have already become
linearly separable by this layer.
Subsequent layers are simply increasing
the spacing between classes. So if after
training the entire network, you were to
terminate after training it, you are
supposed you were to throw away the
final two layers and just attach a
linear classifier over here, that is
still going to work just fine. And very
often this classifier may classifier may
in fact generalize a little more than
the one that use the final two layers
because by the time you got here the
classes have already become linearly
separable.
That make sense to everybody?
Yes or no?
Right. Awesome.
Right. So, any questions about what
we've done so far?
Yes or no? Any questions? No questions.
Just say no. If no questions. So, which
last last part, Georgina?
This one. So,
>> about the layers.
>> Okay. So these are the outputs of the
various layers and the animation is
showing what happens as you train the
network in each case. So here you're
showing how it moves things around as
you train the network till it finds a
position such that when this plane is
warped and it's projected onto the final
W, it learns a perfect classifier. here
uh as you train the network you can see
how it moves the data around until they
become linearly separable and uh at some
point when they've already become
linearly separable subsequent layers
just keep increasing the spacing between
the layers so sonic it could be
overfitting we don't really know right
it might just be increasing the margin
it is a fact however that if you
attached a classifier to this guy this
two should perform just fine on the
training data
Okay. So, any other questions?
No. Okay.
So, let me continue.
So, we've seen what the network learns
here. We've seen what the rest of the
network does. What does it do in the
very first layer? Let's go and take a
look at that a little more closely.
Right. And
now, in the first layer, each of these
neurons is a perceptron. And just for
interpret intuition sake, I'm going to
assume that it's a threshold activation
perceptron. What does a threshold
activation perceptron do? It computes a
weighted sum of the inputs and compares
it to a threshold. If it exceeds the
weighted sum exceeds a threshold, it
outputs a one. Otherwise, it outputs a
zero. The weighted sum of the inputs can
be written as the inner product of a
weights vector, which is basically the
vector of all weights and the input
vector. So the threshold activation
neuron actually performs this
computation. It computes an inner
product of the inputs and the weight and
compares this inner product to a
threshold. If this inner product is
greater than the threshold, it outputs a
one. Otherwise, it outputs a zero. Is
this making sense? Do you guys are are
you okay with this?
Yes or no?
Okay. Can I get like five thumbs ups?
Okay, good. But then what is this inner
product actually?
Uh, and here's what the inner Okay,
those of you who know math, all of you
know math, right? What is x do w? What
is the inner product between two
vectors?
Anyone? What is it?
It's mod x mod w cos theta right
where theta is the angle between the two
vectors. Do you guys remember this?
Okay. Now in highdimensional spaces all
vectors are more or less the same
length. This is a mathematical fact. All
if you if you restrict the volume of the
sphere hypersphere within which the data
lie and in any real world data it's
always restricted it means that very a
very large fraction up to 99.9% of the
data maybe more end up within a small
epsil epsilon of the surface itself
which means all data points are more or
less the same length. So mod x is going
to be the same for pretty much all data.
Mod w is of course just the length of
the vector. So this guy is kind of a
constant. So t over mod x mod w is some
other constant. Let me call this theta
hat. Right? So when I say xrpose w is
greater than theta, it means cos theta
uh let me call this alpha. Right? cos
theta has to be greater than alpha or
theta has to be less than cos inverse
alpha.
Is this making sense to you guys that
this neuron is going to fire if the
angle between x and w is less than
something. So basically the W represents
a template
and what the perceptron is doing is
checking whether all of whether your
your data point X lies within some angle
theta which is cos inverse of alpha of
w. If it lies within this threshold,
it's going to output a one within this
cone. Otherwise, it's going to output a
zero. That's what it does. Is this
making sense? Yes. No.
Right? So in other words,
your perceptron is a correlation filter.
It's computing the correlation between W
and the vector X. If the correlation is
higher than some threshold, it fires.
Otherwise, it fails to fire. So for
example, if you're working on an LED
grid of this kind and you wanted to
build a perceptron that detects the
number two, all you would do is to draw
a two on this grid. This becomes your
weights vector and then subse sub
subsequently anytime you got an input
you'd compute the inner product between
your input and w which is the
correlation between the two and if the
inner product is low you'd say this is
not a two. If the inner product exceeds
some threshold that you set you're going
to agree that it's a two. So the pipron
just measures similarity to a uh
template which is given by the weight
vector.
Is this okay? Are you guys okay with
this intuition?
Right? And so
suppose I were to build a network of
this kind which looks at you know these
LED grids like those old digital watches
and calculators that you used to get and
all it has to do is to determine if the
pattern within this grid is a digit or
not. You give it lots and lots of
examples and you train the network to
classify. But then the first level
features neurons neurons are the first
layer layer they they directly connect
to the input and their weights represent
the templates that these neurons detect
in the input template patterns. And so
you may find up finding out that this
first neuron ends up detecting
horizontal patterns of this kind. The
second one detects horizontal patterns
of this kind. The third one detects
horizontal patterns of this kind and so
on. And so the six the next layer
neurons just combine these guys to form
more complex patterns which might be the
individual digits and the final guy is
just going to fire if a if a sufficient
number of these guys fire. That's how it
detects digits. The key point is that
the first layer neurons end up capturing
the significant features of the input
sub sub patterns of the input that can
be used to make the final decision. Is
that making sense?
Yes. Right. Okay. So now suppose I were
to do this, right? I train this network.
Then I throw this guy away. This is all
gone. And all I do is this. I start off
by drawing an empty grid.
And then I feed this network an input
and check if this guy has fired or not.
If this guy is fired, then I look at the
weight pattern over here. Fill this
empty grid with this weight pattern.
Then I check this guy. If it is not
fire, if it is not fired, I let it be.
Check this guy. If it is fired, I find
the weight pattern and fill in the grid
with this weight pattern. If I do this
and inspect each one of these guys and
fill in these this grid with the weights
of these neurons which did fire, then
how do I what would I expect it to
reconstruct? What would I expect to get
back? Anyone?
What would I expect to get back?
Do the question make sense? I've trained
the network. You'd expect to see the
digit again, right?
Each of them is trying to detect a
feature
which is some pattern in the input. If
the network has fired, it means that
pattern is present in the input. So I
can just fill it up, right? If this
network has fired, if this neuron is
fired, it means this pattern is present
in the input. So I can just go and draw
this guy over here. If this neuron has
fired, you know, I know that this
pattern is present in the input. So I
can go and draw this over here. So if I
just check which of these neurons have
fired and fill up the input with their
weights, I would expect to get back
something that looks like the original
itself. Yes or no?
Right? So this is to go back to CU's
question. would I actually get back the
digit or would I get something less?
So in the case of digits, I might get
back the digit. But for more general
inputs, I cannot guarantee anything
because these guys are only going to
learn those features that are relevant
to detect whether the input is a digit
or not. So for example, it could find
out all of these sub patterns, but they
could also learn to detect patterns like
these. If you find a pattern like this,
it's definitely not a digit. So they
will only learn to detect patterns which
are absolutely indicative indicative of
whether the input is likely to be a
digit or not. Anything that any pattern
that doesn't contribute to this decision
will not be learned. So if I fill up
this guy using the patterns detected by
this by these neurons, I'm going to get
something that approximates the input.
The portions that I would lose are the
portions that are not relevant to the
classification itself. That make sense
to everybody?
Yes or no?
Can I get like 10 5 6 7 8 9 10 seven.
Okay. So what is the computation being
performed? If the output of this network
is Y or let me call this Z I call this Y
and if I recombine
there are you know their outputs the
patterns detect by detected by these
neurons the actual output when I'm
filling up the grid again with these
weights what I'm actually doing is
performing
W
transpose Y the input is wx I'm putting
the threshold activation on
and then I'm multiplying them by
wranspose and that's what the spilling
up business is.
Okay, so of course if I just start with
this network I'm not going to
reconstruct the input but then you know
if I did that then signal will be
partially reconstructed but it's only
going to retain components that
uh are relevant to whether it's a digit
or not. it's only going to retain those
distinctly digit-like or obviously not
digit-like features. The rest are
irrelevant to the classification and
will will be lost. But then
instead of just restricting myself to
those features, how about I build a
network to reconstruct the input itself?
In this case, I'm going to perform the
exact same thing. I'm going to perform
wranspose y where y is the output of
this network. And now I'm going to train
the network to actually minimize the
error between X hat and X. In this case,
it's going to these neurons are going to
learn to detect all features that are
important to reconstruct the input
rather than just for classification. And
so then this network could actually
learn to reconstruct the input. Anything
that it misses are probably noisy
patterns that do not contribute anything
consistent features. That make sense?
Yes. No.
Like a single thumbs up. Okay, guys.
We're slow. All right. So, this network
which learns to reconstruct the input is
what is called an autoenccoder. There's
an encoder which learns to detect the
significant patterns in the signal and
the decoder which recomposes the signal
from these patterns. So what is an
autoenccoder of this kind? To understand
this, let's go back to the simplest
possible autoenccoder which has just one
neuron, one hidden neuron. And to
simplify things further, instead of
using a threshold activation or any
other activation, let's assume that it
has a linear activation. What will this
learn?
Now this network computes right here it
computes a z equals wx
but then y this is an if I initially
assume that it's just a linear
activation an identity activation then
it's y= z and the output as we saw is
going to be wrpose y right which is
simply wrpose
wx
and so now if train the network to
minimize the L2 error between these two
guys. Then what I am doing is minimizing
x - 2 the squared error norm between x -
x i hat which is x - wrpose wx. And so
I'm learning the network parameters to
minimize this squared norm. What is
this? What is the w that minimizes the
squared norm? Anybody recognize this
equation? This guy. I'm trying to find a
w that minimizes this. What is this?
This is just principal component
analysis. Y let's say Z equals
WX, right? Then the output A equals
Wrpose
Z. So if I have a vector W,
every reconstruction is basically just
some scaling of W, right? Because the
output is just Wrpose Z. It doesn't
matter where the input actually lies in
this space. By the time it comes out
here, it's going to be a point on this
vector. That making sense?
Yes or no?
Because the output is always wrpose Z,
which is some scaling of Wrpose and Z is
a scaler. Can I see 10 thumbs ups for
that if this made sense?
Okay. Eight. All right. So basically I'm
trying to find the W such that when I
project every data point onto it the
squared error is minimized that is just
PCA. It's going to find the principal
direction for the data.
So and so the autoenccoder is going to
find the direction of maximum energy. If
the input is zero mean then it's going
to find the direction of maximum
variance.
All input vectors are mapped onto a
point on on this principal axis as I
just mentioned.
So anytime I vary this hidden
representation because the output is
always written,
this weight and this weight different,
it doesn't matter. This U is still going
to represent the principal
subspace because eventually the output
is just some scaling of this U. The
output is Uranspose Z. And so this
network is going to learn to perform
principal component analysis and the
output weight is going to be the minimum
error direction or the principal on
vector for the data. Did this make sense
to everybody?
Then this guy is always going to be the
principal vector if the activation here
is linear.
Yes. No. That make sense? Can I see 10
thumbs ups?
Five. Six. All right.
Now,
what happens if I have more than one
neuron over here?
The output. The solution is still the
same here. I'm going to get y = wx xhat=
wrpose y which is wrppose wx. I'm
finding this w that minimizes the
squared norm. So that means the output
is always going to be some linear
combination of the columns of what or
the rows of w which is going to be some
principal subspace. Right? So the output
of the hidden layer is going to be the
output of this network is going to be a
point on some subspace linear subspace
where the dimensionality of the subspace
is the number of neurons and if you
optimize this network it's going to
learn the principal subspace so that
this error is minimized. If these boys
have linear activation this network will
always perform principal component
analysis.
that clear to everybody?
Yes. Now,
okay. So, moving on. That gives you the
third point.
Okay, 10 seconds, guys.
Okay. What are the answers?
True and true, right? An autoenccoder
with a linear activation performs
principal component analysis of the
input. An autoenccoder with linear
activation, so the hidden layer that has
been trained on some data can only
output values on the principal subspace
of the data regardless of the input.
So some terminology, the portion that
reconstructs the data wranspose y, this
is what we'll call the decoder.
constructing data and the portion that
learns the by that that computes the buy
from the input we are going to call the
encoder. The encoder is the analysis net
which computes a hidden representation
on the principal subspace. The decoder
is the synthesis portion which
reconmposes the data from this hidden
representation of Y. Y is in lower
dimensions than the data itself. Here
it's four dimensional. The data are
seven dimensional. So the encoder learns
a four-dimensional representation from
seven dimensions. Here the decoder is
the one that reconstructs the
seven-dimensional data from the four
dimensions by using these as coordinates
in the W space.
That's when the activation of the
network of the decoder is linear. But
what in a neural network the decoder is
not linear, right? The the activations
are not linear. What happens if the
activations are nonlinear?
When the decoder layers have nonlinear
activations, the network still performs
principal component analysis but except
that it performs nonlinear principal
component analysis. As we saw earlier,
when you have nonlinear activations, it
warps and bends the spa the sheet. So
here what this decoder will learn is a
warping of a fourdimensional plane in
seven dimensions. And so it actually
learns a warped four-dimensional
manifold in seven-dimensional space such
that all the data are as close as
possible to this manifold. That make
sense?
Yes or no?
I see like one. Yes.
So
any so what was unclear about that?
Okay. So in general what we find is that
the decoder actually and the the the
decoder of the network this network
actually performs nonlinear principal
component analysis principal manifold
analysis where it finds a lower
dimensional curved surface such that all
the data it captures most of the
variation in the data and the
dimensionality of this curved surface is
the dimensionality of the hidden
representation.
So
with nonlinearity
this autoenccoder performs nonlinear PCA
and this decoder can be have arbitrary
structure. Deeper networks will capture
more complicated manifolds for the data.
These are deep autoenccoders.
So here are some examples. Here I have
data on a helix
and this you can see that the principal
uh uh variation is just along the helix.
Right?
So here we trained a network with uh
five it's it's an encoder with five
residual res residual blocks each with
64 hidden uh units. The decoder is the
mirror image of the encoder and you can
see what happens once you train the
network. The decoder is only able to
reconstruct this helix. it actually
captures the structure of the helix and
the encoder learns a zv valueue which is
a position on the helix. Of course, it
doesn't learn the actual helix
perfectly. It it seems to have learned
something that goes like this and jumps
here as you know if you start from a low
value of z and keep increasing it. It
follows the helix but then jumps over
here goes out here and then jumps over
here and it does some wonky stuff here.
What do you think is happening out in
these regions? Anyone? What's happening
there?
What do you think is happening?
Anybody?
So here is what happens right since you
this
we have just it we don't we have not
specified any ZV value. the Z range is
being learned. So we don't know whether
what the ZV value is going to be for
data here and what the ZV value is going
to be for data here. All we know is that
if I keep varying Z from minus infinity
to infinity, this guy can only
reconstruct data on the helix. But then
these are ZV values that were not seen
in the training data. And so in Z values
that were not seen in the training data,
this this decoder can do some pretty
bizarre stuff. But in the ranges of Z
that were actually computed with you
know derived from the training data by
the encoder it actually captures the
helix perfectly.
That making sense to everybody.
Yes. No.
Two yeses. Okay.
So here's another example. This time
with a sinosoid. Same thing. And if I
learn a decoder again, you see that the
primary principal variation is the
sinosoid. So the decoder learns to
reconstruct the sinosoid exactly after I
train the network. If I throw away the
encoder and vary the Z from minus
infinity to infinity, it actually
reconstructs the sinosoid except out
here which are Z values that were not
seen in the training data. So it doesn't
generalize. It learns the manifold that
the data lie on though it doesn't
generalize beyond the manifold.
Right? So Bruno will get more of that
later.
And when the hidden dimensionality is of
a lower representation is of a lower
dimensionality of the input, this is
called a bottleneck. Performs nonlinear
principle mac component analysis and
learns the manifold of the data if
properly trained. So then the decoder
can only generate data on the manifold
that the training data lie on. This also
makes it an excellent generator for the
distribution of the training data. Any
values applied to the hidden uh input to
the decoder will produce data similar to
the training data. To to see what I mean
in this case the training data's
principal structure is that of a helix.
Once I train data this this autoenccoder
if I throw away the encoder and just use
this portion of the network then
regardless of what value of Z I give it
if Z is in the range of the training
data it's always going to construct
produce an output that lies on the
principal manifold of the data which
happens to be a helix in this case so uh
using that principle let's see a couple
of cute examples here if I learn an
autoenccod digit data then I just use
the decoder. If I feed it any odd input,
so long as the Z's in the input lie in
the same range as the training data, the
output is going to look somewhat like a
digit.
Right? This is nonlinear principle
component analysis.
And because the network has infinite
capacity, it won't generalize outside
the Z's that it has not seen.
Now, here is an example where we trained
an autoenccoder
on uh examples of music, spectrograms of
music from a saxophone. Then having
trained it, we threw away the encoder
and then we feed the decoder with some
random inputs.
And if I treat the decoder with random
inputs, what do I get? Here's one
example.
It actually outputs something that
sounds like a saxophone, right? Here's
another example.
Also a different sound but also from a
saxophone. So in other words, the
autoenccoder, the decoder of the
autoenccoder has learned the manifold of
saxophone sounds. And so anytime you
provide it an input which is within the
range of data that it's seen in the
training data, it's only going to
produce stuff that sounds like a
saxophone.
Or here's another one where we used a
clarinet. And again
it's not a pure tone but it's a clarinet
sound like it could be a mixture of
notes right you can see how it has
learned the clarinet manifold did this
example make sense to you guys
yes or no right beautiful huh and so
here is your fourth poll before I
I'll give you only 30 seconds for this.
10 seconds, guys.
All right.
Anybody want to give me the answers?
What are the answers?
All right. An autoenccoder with
nonlinear activation performs nonlinear
principal component analysis. It finds
the principal manifold near which the
training data lies. The decoder can only
generate data on this principal manifold
regardless of the input. And so the
decoder is a dictionary which composes
data like the training data in response
to any input.
And I've actually close off I'm going to
close off today with a cute little
example of application of this property
signal separation. Given a mixed sound
from multiple sources, we want to
separate out the sources. Now there's a
standard approach to this called a
dictionary based technique. Let's say I
want to have recordings of drums and
guitars. I want to learn to separate the
guitar from the drums. The basic idea is
that you learn a dictionary of building
blocks for each source. So you'd learn a
dictionary of all the all the uh sub
structures of guitar sounds, a different
dictionary from the examples of drum
sounds of all the substructures of of
drum sounds. And then when you get a
mixed recording, you see how entries
from this dictionary and this end
dictionary must be combined to compose
the mixed recording.
And then because you know exactly which
components of this dictionary and and
this dictionary can it be used, you can
actually uh you know uh we can use this
to reconstruct the separated sources.
So in our example I'm going to learn an
autoenccoder from say the guitar sound
and an autoenccoder from the drum sound.
Once I do this I know that the decoder
of this autoenccoder can only generate
guitar-like sounds. That's what we saw.
The decoder of this guy can only
generate drumlike sounds. We saw this
guy. So now when I get a mixed recording
of guitar and drums,
all I will need to do is to figure out
what was the input to this decoder and
what were the inputs to this decoder and
this decoder. So that when their outputs
were combined, the combination
looks like the mixed sound in the
specttoraphic domain. So basically I'm
going to define an L2 error between the
output of this network and my input. I
back propagate that error not to learn
network parameters because those have
been learned, right? They were learned
out here. I'm going to use that to
figure out the inputs to these two
decoders. And then once I figured them
out,
the output of this decoder in response
to this input should be sound one. And
to this input should be sound two. And
when you add them up, you should be
getting the mixed sound. So let's see
how this works. Here was an example of
it's a very simp. It's a it's a it's a
wind instrument and a string instrument.
Uh but they produce very similar sounds.
But then we used some separate
recordings from both to learn a
dictionary an autoenccoder for both both
both types of sounds. In each case the
decoder was a five layer network 600
units wide. So that's our five layer
dictionary and then we use this approach
to try to separate out the two source
sounds. So, here's the mixed recording,
and here's what it pulls out for the
first one.
Here's the original.
Here's the spot it pulls out for the
second one.
It's pretty good, huh? Again, we're
using a very simple principle that the
autoenccoder learns the principal
manifold of the source data. I'm just
using that this application to
illustrate that this is what in fact
happens and I think it's a pretty good
demonstration. Right? So
the story for the day classification
networks learn to predict the a
posterior probability of classes. The
network until the final layer is a
feature extractor that converts the
input to be almost linearly separable.
The final layer is a classifier that
operates on the linearly separable data.
Uh the neural network can also be used
to perform linear or nonlinear principle
auto component analysis
using autoenccoders which can be used to
compose constructive dictionaries for
data which in turn can be used to model
data distributions. We'll build on that
in the next couple of classes. So I went
over by a minute. I apologize for that.
Are there any questions?
A reminder that class is in person.